<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration and ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for the better securing and setling of the peace of the county of Kent, and for enabling them to associate with the City of London, or any other counties adjacent. And to raise forces within the said county, as well horse as foot, and therewith to give, or cause battell to be given to all such forces as are or shal be raised without the consent of both houses of Parliament; and all such persons with their abbettors and adherents to invade, resist, put to flight, pursue, suppresse, kill, slay, put to execution of death, and by all means to destroy, as enemies to the kingdom. Likewise, instructions for the lord-lieutenant, deputy-lieutenants, and other offiers [sic], and commanders in the county of Kent. And, that every person which shall be imployed as souldiers in this service, of the age of 16. yeers and upwards, shall solemnly take an oath, to be approved of by the Parliament, and they that wilfully neglect the same shall be proceeded against as delinquents, and enemies of the peace of the kingdom. Die Martis, 30 Maii. 1643. Ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that this declaration and ordinance with the instructions shall be forthwith printed and published. J. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E104_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13977</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859590</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82586)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 18:E104[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration and ordinance of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, for the better securing and setling of the peace of the county of Kent, and for enabling them to associate with the City of London, or any other counties adjacent. And to raise forces within the said county, as well horse as foot, and therewith to give, or cause battell to be given to all such forces as are or shal be raised without the consent of both houses of Parliament; and all such persons with their abbettors and adherents to invade, resist, put to flight, pursue, suppresse, kill, slay, put to execution of death, and by all means to destroy, as enemies to the kingdom. Likewise, instructions for the lord-lieutenant, deputy-lieutenants, and other offiers [sic], and commanders in the county of Kent. And, that every person which shall be imployed as souldiers in this service, of the age of 16. yeers and upwards, shall solemnly take an oath, to be approved of by the Parliament, and they that wilfully neglect the same shall be proceeded against as delinquents, and enemies of the peace of the kingdom. Die Martis, 30 Maii. 1643. Ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that this declaration and ordinance with the instructions shall be forthwith printed and published. J. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for I. Wright in the Old-baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iune 1. 1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kent (England) --  History, Military --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155942:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155942:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION AND ORDINANCE Of the LORDS and COMMONS Aſſembled in Parliament, For the better ſecuring and ſetling of the peace of the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and for enabling them to aſſociate with the City of <hi>London,</hi> or any other Counties adjacent. And to raiſe Forces within the ſaid County, as well Horſe as Foot, and therewith to give, or cauſe battell to be given to all ſuch forces as are or ſhal be raiſed without the conſent of both houſes of Parliament; and all ſuch perſons with their Abbettors and Adherents to invade, reſiſt, put to flight, purſue, ſuppreſſe, kill, ſlay, put to execution of death, and by all means to deſtroy, as enemies to the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, Inſtructions for the Lord-Lieutenant, Deputy-Lieutenants, and other Offiers, and Commanders in the County of <hi>Kent.</hi> And, that every perſon which ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as Souldiers in this ſervice, of the age of 16. yeers and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, ſhall ſolemnly take an Oath, to be approved of by the Parliament, and they that wilfully neglect the ſame ſhall be proceeded againſt as Delinquents, and enemies of the peace of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Die Martis, 30 Maii. 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ORdered by the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that this Declaration and Ordinance with the Inſtructions ſhall be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>J. Brown Cler. Parliamentorum:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>I. Wright</hi> in the Old-baily, <hi>Iune</hi> 1. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:155942:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Die Martis,</hi> 30 <hi>Maii.</hi> 1643. A Declaration and Ordinance of the Lords and Commons in Parliament, for the better ſecuring and ſetling of the Peace of the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> and for enabling them to aſſociate with the City of <hi>London,</hi> or any other Counties adjacent.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lords and Commons now in Parliament aſſembled, being certainely informed, and by ſad experience finding it true, That divers Papiſts, Traytors, Delinquents and other perſons ill affected to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, have Trayterouſly combined and aſſociated themſelves in this Kingdome, for the utter extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the true Proteſtant well affected party therein; And for that end have raiſed and daily doe raiſe great Forces both of Horſe and Foot, and have plundered, ſpoyled, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed multitudes of His Majeſties good Subjects, uſing alſo their utmoſt endeavours to bring in to their aſſiſtance Forraigners of their owne Faction, All which if not ſpéedily prevented will utterly ſubvert the true Proteſtant Religion, (which is their chiefe deſigne) the Lawes of the Land, the priviledges of Parliament, and the Liberty of the Subject: For the timely preventing and withſtanding of which miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous deſignes, the well affected of the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> have been and ſtill are deſirous to have a conſiderable move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing body of Horſe and Foot raiſed and maintained at the
<pb facs="tcp:155942:2"/>charge of the ſaid County, and to enter into aſſociation for the mutuall defence and preſervation of the peace of the ſaid County, and of all thoſe that ſhall joyne with them therein: The ſaid Lords and Commons doe thereupon declare that they hold it a thing moſt fit and neceſſary for the preſent ſtate of the kingdome, and ſecurity of the ſaid County of <hi>Kent;</hi> And do ordaine and declare, and be it ordained and declared by the ſaid Lords and Commons, that the Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-lieutenants, Collonels, Captaines, and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers that are or ſhall be imployed in the ſaid County of <hi>Kent,</hi> the County and City of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Cinqueports, with their members, and all other well affected perſons inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in them, or any of them, ſhall and may aſſociate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves each with other, and with all thoſe who ſhall enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Aſſociation; And that the ſaid Lord lieutenant and Deputy-lieutenants, or any ſeven or more of them, for the foreſaid ends and purpoſes, and alſo for the forcing and compelling refractory perſons to yeeld obedience unto the Orders and Ordinances of either or both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall have full Power and Authority, and are hereby authoriſed to raiſe, arme, and maintaine a moving body of Foot, conſiſting of one Thouſand or more Voluntiers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of none to be of the Trained-bands; and one or more Troope or Troopes of Horſe which now are or hereafter ſhall be ſubſcribed or otherwiſe provided within the ſaid County, whereof none alſo are to be taken out of the Trained Forces: And alſo to nominate, conſtitute, and appoint a Major Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall over the ſaid Forces, and to give full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the ſaid Major Generall, in caſe of ſickneſſe or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability of body, from time to time conſtitute and appoint in his ſtead ſuch truſty and able perſon as he ſhall thinke fit to be his Deputy, and in his abſence to doe all things belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Office of a Major Generall: And the ſaid Lord-lieutenant, and Deputy-Lieutenants, or any ſeaven or
<pb facs="tcp:155942:3"/>more of them, ſhall be, and are hereby authoriſed to Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and appoint Collonels, Lieutenant-collonels, Serjeant-maiors, Captaines, and other Officers over the ſaid Forces: and from time to time, in and into all convenient places to Leade, Conduct, Quarter, and Exerciſe, or cauſe to be lead, conducted, quartered, and exerciſed, the ſaid Forces, or any part thereof, and therewith to give or cauſe battaile to be given to all ſuch Forces as are or ſhall be raiſed againſt, or without authority or conſent of both Houſes of Parliament, or that ſhall make or endeavour to make any Invaſion, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Tumult, or Inſurrection, or ſhall plunder, pillage, or deſtroy any of His Maieſties good Subiects, And all and ſingular ſuch perſons, their abbettors, and adherents, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade, reſiſt, put to flight, purſue, ſuppreſſe, kill, flay, put to execution of death, and by all meanes to deſtroy as Enemies to the kingdome: And to performe, and cauſe to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all things elſe which they ſhall in their iudgements thinke néedfull, as well for the preſervation and ſafety of the peace of the ſaid County and places aforeſaid, as of all thoſe which ſhall ioyne in the ſaid Aſſociation, obſerving the Inſtructions hereunto annexed, with ſuch other Directions, and Commands as they ſhall receive from time to time from both Houſes of Parliament, or from his Excellency the Earle of <hi>Eſſex.</hi> And be it alſo Declared and Ordained, by the authority aforeſaid, That the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty-lieutenants, and other Inhabitants of the ſaid County, and every of them, and every other perſon which is or ſhall be imployed in that ſervice, in what they have any way al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done towards the preparing and perfecting ſo neceſſary a worke, or ſhall hereafter doe or performe in purſuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſhall be ſaved and kept harmleſſe by the Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Parliament: And the ſaid Lords and Commons doe hereby Declare and Ordaine, that neither the ſaid Forces, nor any part of them ſhal or may at any time
<pb facs="tcp:155942:3"/>be removed out of the ſaid County without ſpeciall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Direction from both Houſes of Parliament, or from his Excellency the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> unleſſe it be to the ayd and aſſiſtance of the Counties with whom they ſhal enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſſociation, and in purſuance of their ſaid aſſociation: And for the better ordering and mannaging of the ſaid Forces of Horſe and Foote, Be it declared and ordained, by the authority aforeſaid, That the ſaid Lord-lieutenant, and Deputy-lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or any ſeven or more of them ſhall have hereby full po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and authority to make, give and execute the ſame Orders and Inſtructions for regulating and puniſhing the Officers, Troopers, and Souldiers of the ſaid Forces, as his Excellency the Lord Generall hath done in his Army, and to compell them to obedience, as occaſion ſhall require. And the better to defend the ſaid County and Inhabitants thereof from all invading, plundering and pillaging, and that ſpéedy meanes may be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the furniſhing and providing of Horſes, Armes, and Ammunition, making Fortifications, payment of Officers, and other neceſſary charges, And for the repayment of all ſuch ſums of money as are or hath béen already, or ſhall be advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and ſubſcribed, towards the forwarding of this worke: It is hereby declared and ordained, That forthwith, and from time to time untill the ſaid Forces ſhall by authority of both Houſes be disbanded, there be raiſed by way of taxe or rate within the ſaid County and places aforeſaid ſuch ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the intents aforeſaid, as to the Lord-lieutenant, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty-lieutenants, or any ſeven or more of them ſhall be thought requiſite and neceſſary: And that the Deputy-Lieutenants or any thrée or more of them after thrée moneths next enſuing the firſt ſeſſement made by vertue of this Ordinance, ſhall iſſue forth their ſeverall Warrants unto ſuch perſons as by them or any three of them have béen or ſhall be conſtituted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Treaſurers or Receivers of ſuch ſums of money as have béen, or at any time hereafter, before the ſaid ſeſſement or
<pb facs="tcp:155942:4"/>any leavies thereupon made, ſhall be lent towards the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this worke for the repayment of the ſame unto the lenders thereof, they the ſaid lenders produceing the Acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance or Acquitances of the ſaid Treaſurers or Receivers for the ſaid moneys lent as aforeſaid.</p>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>Inſtructions for the Lord-lieutenant, Deputy-lieutenants, and others Officers and Commanders in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> the City and County of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Cinqueports, and members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, within the ſaid County of <hi>Kent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THat the Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieutenants of the ſaid County of <hi>Kent,</hi> of the City and County of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the ſaid Cinqueports and members of the ſame, or any two or more of them, doe with all convenient ſpeed ſummon the ſeverall Gentlemen, Freeholders, and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof, as well within the Liberties and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as without, that doe beare, or are able to beare or finde Armes to ſuch places in the ſaid Counties and places afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as they hold moſt fitting; and at ſuch meeting to take a view of what Armes and Forces may be raiſed, beſides the Trained-bands in the ſaid Counties and places, and examine the defects of Armes and Ammunition, and to conſult of ſome ſitting courſe how to have the want of Armes and other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects ſupplied; And at ſuch meetings, or at any other fit time or times the ſaid Deputy-lieutenants, or any two or more of them, ſhall and may propound to all the inhabitants of the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid, that are able to beare or finde Armes, or to contribute towards the ſame, what preſent and iminent danger and neceſſity the Kingdome is now redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced unto by the wicked advice, attempts, and conſpiracies of Papiſts, Traitors, Delinquents, and other ill affected perſons, declaring themſelves againſt the Parliament; And to perſwade and ſtir them up to joyn in a mutuall defence of one another, and of all that ſhall aſſociate with them, to give, provide, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb facs="tcp:155942:4"/>lend, or advance, Horſe, Money, Plate, or Armes, towards the defence &amp; preſervation of the peace of the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid, and towards the raiſing furniſhing and maintaining of the Forces hereby ordained to be raiſed and maintained within the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">II. And for the better leavying of all ſums to be aſſeſſed and ſet upon the ſaid Counties and places, for the defence and preſervation of the ſame as afore ſaid, the ſaid Lord lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Deputy Lieutenants of the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid, or any two or more of them ſhal and may aſſeſſe and taxe, or cauſe to be aſſeſſed and taxed the ſaid ſum and ſums upon the ſeverall Cities, Corporations, Lath, Rapes, Wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, Hundreds, Townes, Hamlets, and Villages in the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid; And that they or any two or more of them ſhal and may nominate and appoint Treaſurers, Collectors, and Aſſeſſors, in the ſaid Counties and places afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, for the aſſeſſing, receiving, and collecting ſuch ſum and ſums of money as aforeſaid; And that the Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants or any two or more of them ſhall and may grant War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants under their hands and feales in writing to any Conſtable, Officer, or any other perſon or perſons whatſoever to raiſe and leavy the ſaid ſum and ſums ſo to be aſſeſſed and taxed as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, by diſtreſſe, ſale of goods, or by ſuch other waies or means, as to the ſaid Deputy-lieutenants, or any two of them ſhal be thought requiſite upon all ſuch perſon and perſons up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom any ſum ſhall be aſſeſſed and ſet as aforeſaid, that do refuſe or neglect to pay the ſame. And in caſe no diſtreſſe is or may be found, then the ſaid Deputy-lieutenants or any two or more of them ſhall and may commit ſuch perſon &amp; perſons ſo refuſing &amp; neglecting to pay as aforeſaid, to ſome common Goale, or to ſuch other place as the ſaid Deputy-lieutenants or any two of them ſhal think fit, there to remaine without baile, or mainprize, untill payment be made of ſuch ſum and ſums as aboveſaid, wherein ſpeciall care ſhal be had and uſed that ſuch ſum and ſums of money ſhall be impoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, taxed and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied
<pb facs="tcp:155942:5"/>upon all Papiſts, Delinquents, and ſuch who have either contributed nothing upon the ſubſcriptions &amp; Propoſitions, or very ſmall and inconſiderable ſums as may in proportion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall the ſubſcriptions and contributions of thoſe who are wel affected and have already liberally contributed and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
               <p n="3">III. That all Sheriffs, Juſtices of the peace, Majors, Bayliffs, Conſtables, and all other His Majeſties Officers, as well within Liberties as without, be from time to time aiding and aſiſting unto the ſaid Lord-lieutenant, &amp; Deputy-lieutenants in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the power now or heretofore to them given by both Houſes of Parliament; And if they ſhal refuſe or forbeare to be aiding and aſſiſting to them therein, that the ſaid Lord-lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Deputy-lieutenants, or any one or more of them, ſhal them apprehend and impriſon, or cauſe them to be apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and impriſoned, or ſent up to the Parliament for further puniſhment as to juſtice ſhall appertaine.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. That if any perſon or perſons being nominated or appointed Seſſors or Collectors by vertue of this Ordinance, ſhall refuſe or neglect to be aiding and aſſiſting in execution of ſuch office ſo enjoyned him or them, That for the firſt neglect of the ſaid ſervice the ſaid Deputy-Lieutenants, or any two of them, ſhall impoſe upon every ſuch Collector or Seſſor ſo refuſing or neglecting the ſaid Service, the ſum of ten pounds by way of mulct; and for his ſecond refuſe all or neglect, ſhall puniſh him with impriſonment till he ſhall conform himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="5">V. That the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or any two or more of them, doe put in execution in the ſaid Counties and Places aforeſaid, as well this preſent Ordinance and Inſtructions, as other Ordinances and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions formerly to them granted by both Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, for raiſing of Money upon the Propoſitions, for the executing of the <hi>Militia,</hi> diſarming of Papiſts and other ill affected perſons, or any other Ordinance or Inſtructions
<pb facs="tcp:155942:5"/>of both Houſes heretofore granted to them &amp; now in forces And for that purpoſe, that they, or any two, or more of them, ſhal have power and authority to Arm, Exerciſe, Train, and put in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as well all and every the trained Bands and Troops of the ſaid Counties and Places aforeſaid, and other Voluntiers both of Horſe and Foot, as the ſaid Forces of Horſe and Foot raiſed or to be raiſed, or maintained by vertue of this preſent Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, as aforeſaid, and them under the command of ſuch Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels, Lieutenant-Colonels, Sergeant-Majors, Captains, and other Officers, as from time to time being nominated by the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy Lieutenants, or any three or more of them, as ſhall be approved of or appointed to lead and conduct the ſaid Forces, as well againſt all forraigne Power that ſhall in hoſtile manner invade the ſaid Counties, as alſo againſt all other Forces which ſhall be either within the ſaid Counties and Places aforeſaid, or elſewhere raiſed to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of the Peace thereof, or which ſhall ſtand in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Orders, Commands, and Ordinances of both Houſes of Parliament. And if any perſon or perſons whatſoever ſhall lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie, or endeavour to leavie, or billet any Souldiers, or raiſe, draw forth, or keepe together the trained Bands of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and places, or other armed Forces thereof by colour or pretence of any Commiſſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Warrant or Authority from his Majeſty under the great Seale, or otherwiſe, without order or conſent of both Houſes of Parliament, That they the Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieutenants, and every of them, are to make knowne to the ſaid Trained-bands and Forces aforeſaid, and other Inhabitants of the ſaid Counties and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforeſaid, that thoſe who ſhall appeare upon any ſuch War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or obey any ſuch Commiſſion ſhall bee held enemies to the publique peace; And thoſe that ſhall not appeare upon any ſuch Warrant and Commiſſion, nor doe any thing in ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, but conforme and ſubmit themſelves to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the <hi>Militia,</hi> and to this Ordinance and the Inſtructions thereupon, ſhall be protected by both Houſes of Parliament, and
<pb facs="tcp:155942:6"/>alſo ſhall make known to the ſaid Inhabitants, That it hath ever been, and ſtill ſhall be the care and endeavours of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to provide for His Majeſties ſafetie; and that they do not, nor never did intend any evill againſt His Majeſties P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon, His Crown, or Dignity, that His greateſt ſafety is in the Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and fidelity of His Subjects, and in the Advice and Councell of His Parliament. And His greateſt danger is in withdrawing Himſelfe from them, and joyning Himſelfe to ſuch diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted and malignant Perſons, obnoxious to Juſtice for their great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ormities, who under colour of doing Him ſervice, have raiſed Forces which they labour to increaſe, to the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zard of ruining Religion and the whole Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. That no Treaſurer or Receiver of Money lent or aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards the raiſing and maintaining of theſe Forces ſhall iſſue out any ſuch Money, but under the hands of the Deputy-Lieutenants, or two or more of them: And that the ſaid Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-Lieutenants ſhall not ſigne or grant any Warrant or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants for the iſſuing or paying of any ſum or ſums of Money, but for the furniſhing of Horſes, Armes, and Ammunition, making Fortifications, paiment of Officers and Souldiers, or r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>parment of the Money already advanced or to be advanced by loane for this Service, or other neceſſary charges tending to the ſafety and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid, and not otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. That the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, beſides the Magazines already within the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid, ſhall out of the Monies to be raiſed as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, provide and furniſh ſuch quantities of Arms, Ammunition, Powder, Match, and Bullet, as ſhall be by them, or any ſeven or more of them thought requiſite and neceſſary for the furniſhing of the ſaid Forces both of Horſe and Foot, to be raiſed, armed, and maintained by vertue of this Ordinance and Inſtructions, and for the ſafety and neceſſary defence of the ſaid Counties, and the ſame being ſo provided to be carefully kept in ſome one or more Magazines for that purpoſe; And that as for ſuch of
<pb facs="tcp:155942:6"/>the ſaid Armes and Ammunion which after the disbanding of the ſaid Forces, as aforeſaid, ſhall remain, full reſtitution ſhall be made of ſo many thereof as are or ſhall be borrowed or lent towards the preſent arming of the ſaid Forces; and the reſidue thereof, ſhall be kept and preſerved in ſtore in publike Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines for the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid.</p>
               <p n="8">VIII. That the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, or any one or more of them, ſhall take away, and cauſe to be taken away, the Arms, Horſes, and Moneys of all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons inhabiting within the Counties and places aforeſaid, as ſhall refuſe to contribute Money, Plate, Horſe, Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or Arms upon the Propoſitions, or upon this Ordinance and Inſtructions, or upon any other Ordinance formerly made and now in force, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to proceed from both Houſes of Parliament And that they or any two of them, ſhall and may in manner aforeſaid, compell all Papiſts, Delinquents, and perſons diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>affected to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to contribute in proportion to their eſtates to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Army raiſed in defence of the Parliament and Kingdome, and to the Forces raiſed or to be raiſed by vertue of this preſent Ordinance and Inſtructions.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. That the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieutenants, and every of them, ſhall take care that the ſaid Forces of Horſe and Foot, raiſed or to be raiſed by vertue of this Ordinance and Inſtructions, ſo long as they ſhall continue in the ſaid County, or any other County that ſhall aſſociate therein, be governed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Lawes and Ordinances publiſhed by his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and bee paid out of ſuch Moneys as ſhall be leavied and paid upon this Ordinance and Inſtructions.</p>
               <p n="10">X. That all and every perſon and perſons w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are or ſhal be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied as Souldiers in this ſervice, or w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are of the age of ſixteen yeers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or upwards, inhabiting in the Counties and places afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhall for the better ſecuring and uniting thereof, ſolemnly take ſuch Covenant or Proteſtation, or forme of Aſſociation, as ſhall be agreed upon, propounded, or approved of by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be taken by all perſons therein exceeding the ſaid age:
<pb facs="tcp:155942:7"/>And that whoſoever ſhall refuſe, or wilfully neglect to take the ſame, ſhall be taken within the intent and meaning of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to be a Delinquent, and an enemy to the good and peace of the ſaid County and Kingdom, and ſo to be proceeded againſt to all intents and purpoſes within this and all other Ordinances and Declarations publiſhed by authority of Parliament.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. That to the end all Orders and Ordinances of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be better divulged, &amp; intelligence received and given from and to the Parliament, and that the ſaid Lord-Lieutenant and Deputy-Lieutenant may upon all occaſions receive Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations concerning the ſtate of the ſaid Counties and places aforeſaid, and determine and advize concerning the ſame. It is therefore ordained, That the ſaid Deputy-Lieutenants be here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by enjoyned conſtantly to conveene once every moneth at the leaſt in ſome one convenient place of the ſaid Countie during the time of theſe publique diſtractions.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, for the better ſecuring of all ſuch Inhabitants of the ſaid County and places aforeſaid, as now are, or hereafter ſhall be voted Delinquents by both Houſes of Parliament, or either of them, or which for their diſobedience or contempt already, or hereafter, expreſſed againſt this or any other Ordinance of Parliament, or other proceedings thereof, or for whatſoever other cauſe ſhall be thought fit by the ſaid Deputy-Lieutenants, or any two of them, to be committed and remaine in ſafe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: The ſaid Deputy-Lieutenants, or any two of them, are hereby authorized to apprehend, or by their Warrant cauſe to be apprehended, and to commit all and ſingular ſuch perſons as aforeſaid unto the next Goale, or to ſuch other place or places as the ſaid Deputy-Lieutenants, or any two of them ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
